good morning professor meadows
um i've really been looking forward to
this conversation for
um quite some time now since since you
agreed to have it
um for me this is a special day because
i've been
aware of your work for 25 years of doing
research and
exploring practice and sustainability
and regenerative
methods to avoid the trajectory that you
warned of
by now 48 years ago with your co-authors
and it's a simple seemingly
obvious truth that you cannot have
exponential growth on a finite planet
but for some reason humanity has
been unable or the
the people in charge or whoever has been
unable
to really respond to this truth in the
appropriate way
and i'm i'm remembering a conversation i
had a couple of years ago
with um dr michael mcdonald who in the
1980s
did some work for the us government
where they ended up with a report in
late 1980s basically saying that if we
wouldn't change our trajectory
by the mid 1990s then
according to their work by the somewhere
between 2030 and 2050
a massive die off of global population
would happen and collapses of ecosystems
would
cascade and obviously we haven't um
made that change and i've also recently
heard heard you a couple of
years ago also make that point and when
the
45th anniversary of limits to growth
happened you basically said there is now
no chance to avoid collapse um
how would you turn that
problem into
a potential do you still see a potential
for us if if we do the right things
as a species and in our communities
locally
to respond to the reality that we're now
heading
for collapse and we're seeing systems
collapse all around us
and what do you think needs to be done
you've spent 50 years of your career
working on this
so at each moment
each of us has uh choices
uh between different actions and some of
those actions will make the future
better than it would have been otherwise
and some of those choices
will make it worse or at least not
improve it very much
that's still true absolutely
however the notion that there is some
sort of
fairly attractive sustainable society
ahead of us if we can only find it i
think is now
a fantasy the
global population its
use of materials its uh
generation of uh wastes
has grown so far above the sustainable
capacity of the planet that uh there is
that there's nothing ahead that it
uh it looks like this um
you know i don't know sustainable utopia
people might talk about
so what can you do well uh
i a global die-off is
of course one possibility you can come
up with a number of realistic
uh scenarios that would produce that
ranging from a
massive volcanic explosion that shuts
down food production
to you know asteroids hitting us and uh
or a really uh vicious uh pandemic
you know it's useful to remember that
this virus we're dealing with now is
actually not a vicious virus it's very
infectious but it's not very lethal
and sars for example was very lethal
but not very infectious it sars killed i
don't know 20 30 percent of the people
infected this one is uh not even able to
manage
uh one percent so if you got something
in both infectious
and lethal then you that would be
another well so those scenarios are
possible but there are also
scenarios in which the system sort of
struggles and through fits and starts
gets down to a
lower level of population and material
flow
i i hope for the second because it means
i
am able within my own community to do
things that
are have a have potential
but now instead of
trying to achieve sustainable
development i am looking for
ways to change achieve what i call
resilient development uh
patterns of social society that are
relatively immune to big shocks
i could get into a lot of detail about
that not relevant here but that's
those are the areas where i see
interesting things to be done now well
i'd
i'd love to just very briefly outline
some of my perspective that resonates
with this
around like i would call it um like in
my book i speak about this
designing regenerative cultures plural
and i
i um invite people through 250 questions
into a process of at their local level
at the
at the by regional scale the wider
watershed that their community is
um set in to explore these questions in
order to
what i engage in what i would call a
dual pathway which is on the one hand
um the resilience building for
the disruptions that are just going to
come hitting harder and faster in the
next two or three decades
but at the same time by engaging people
really in
local ecosystems restoration and um
carbon drawdown but through
biosequestration not through large
geoengineering projects but
through soil building reforestation new
forms of agriculture
a shift to a new material culture that
is more biomaterials based and locks
carbon through biomaterials into our
products of use that i i sense that
a lot of what we're now seeing those
systems are all collapsing and they're
collapsing partially because they're
patterns that no longer serve and that
cannot be sustained
but um what i would hope is that because
this dual path of preparing for the
worst
and trying to engage in
um drawing down carbon and healing
ecosystems
we might just if we engage all of her
humanity in global solidarity in this
which i know is
is a utopian in and of itself to some
extent
um we might still have a snowball's
chance in hell if we decide to do this
relatively quickly would you would you
say that that is
also too optimistic
well you've covered a lot of ground with
your uh narrative
um some of which seemed
to me uh quite uh
fantastical and others uh perhaps
realistic
uh let's put this in uh context
we or you use the term collapse
actually we never used that term in any
of our work
uh i i don't think it generates
um useful thinking
uh and and it's actually uh from
some perspectives not accurate from the
perspective of industrial society or
from the perspective
of uh our species
uh some things are collapsing now
uh uh the climate uh is
changing drastically etc but from the
perspective of the planet
you know it's not a collapse it's simply
moving over into a new mode
of uh behavior i was
talking about these issues recently with
a friend and
he uh you know became alarmed and said
oh my goodness we have to
uh save the planet and i said no we
don't have to save the planet the planet
knows how to save itself it's uh been
doing that for several hundred million
years and i have
absolute confidence is going to keep
doing it for another
couple hundred million years till the
sun blows up yeah anyway
and uh so it's we don't have to save the
planet
uh what's of concern to us is whether we
can save
some of the elements of what we consider
to be
an acceptable decent attractive
lifestyle
so uh process collapsing for
you know for most everybody else it's
not actually the
critters in my backyard uh are enjoying
uh
the virus it's uh reduced the amount of
traffic on the road and
the noise levels etc you know so it's
just a question of perspective
and just to clarify when i use the word
collapse and mine i mean collapse in the
context of
um if you if you think of buzz hollings
work on um
the adaptive cycle and systems that you
that you do have phases
in in the sort of what he called a
panicky you have this nested system
where you find collapses and happening
at different scales
and both temporally and spatially and
they're really just
a dissolution of system structures and
patterns that no longer serve
and that then enable the reorganization
to
have a new loop of um innovation so
so i agree that gaia will be fine
without us um
but so i admired buzz i actually worked
under him uh when he
briefly ran the institute for applied
systems analysis in vienna
and i i gained a lot from his work i'd
have to go back and look i'm not sure he
used the term collapse
you know he was interested in different
dynamic uh behavior patterns
i think in this connection it may be
useful
and again trying to give you a
a a framework within which you can
discuss this idea of what you can do
uh we are uh confronted
with a variety of different uh
existential issues the virus is
actually one of them uh nuclear
proliferation
climate change uh and and many others
i find it useful to uh separate these
into two categories
universal and global universal problems
uh affect everybody uh but they manifest
locally and there are things you can do
locally to reduce their
problems and and when you invest in
local solutions
rather soon and rather nearby
there's benefit that's uh such things as
a
water contamination noise
uh let's say deforestation everybody
suffers from deforestation but uh in
nigeria or in texas
or in china you can do something about
it
and realize the benefits without waiting
for the whole rest of the planet
uh to fall in line and help out other
problems like nuclear proliferation
climate change uh and
and now i will say this virus uh are
global problems
there is a virtually nothing you can do
locally
uh to solve the problem you need for
everybody to get
on board and agree about a solution
this distinction is useful and in my
thinking because i see
no hope whatsoever for achieving
a solution to global problems i i just
do not
see any basis in history or anything in
the current news to suggest
that suddenly people are going to start
sacrificing what they perceive to be in
their own short-term best interest
for the better and longer term good
these issues like climate change will
resolve themselves but they're going to
uh produce uh solutions that are imposed
on us not ones that we
proactively develop now within the
context of possibilities that
we're left with from all the global
problems there are many useful things to
do i
i work uh in a small town in central new
hampshire
which still has uh for example quite a
bit of undeveloped land and
uh i'm working to put legal restrictions
on it so that it doesn't
get developed and i'm working with
others to you know build hiking trails
and so forth
we can make durham slightly more
attractive
in that respect without waiting for
beijing
or new york or moscow to decide that
they're interested
in these things so when you ask what can
you do
i suggest look for
the universal problems and there
typically
a small group of people working in
alignment uh
can have a significant constructive
impact
yeah no i completely agree with that
and i mean for a long part of my work
i've been working with the eco village
movement
and the transition town movement and
engaging people
with basically local resilience building
and doing
what they can in their region um
creating
models of more sustainable ways of
living um
i i do sense that we're now at a point
where we're beginning to wake up that if
we all did this
well in our bioregions i think the shift
that i've made
is that i used to be very focused on the
very small community scale
like neighborhood size or intentional
community size a few hundred people a
few
thousand people and um what i've
come to see is that the the systemic
integration
of how to meet basic needs of a
population within
a given spatial context you need a
little
larger area than just a community and
and so the bioregional approach that has
been around for a long time but
but has found it hard to sort of get off
the ground
um is something that i i see a lot of
people converging on now
um do you have any comments on on the
difference between working
like as we're working more on universal
problems
at the local stroke regional level um
how do you see that the relationship
between
those scales that the small community
scale and the wider region of the
community sits
in well first of all i'd comment that
uh at least for myself i'm always
skeptical about my opinions because i
realize
the extent to which each of us moves in
a
information bubble which tends to be
self-confirming
uh you know i i used to call this the
boston san francisco syndrome i would
work in i taught for a while in boston
and i would fly out and talk to my
colleagues in san francisco
and they had the same opinions and uh
were worried about the same things as
we were in boston and i would sort of
then look at a map of the united states
and say my gosh
look at the whole country is uh moving
in the right direction and of course
if i'd stopped off in des moines or uh
ohio or
montana on the way between the two
cities i would have been forced to have
a different opinion
and now it's not only your social circle
but
it's the algorithms on google which
decide which pieces of news
you're likely to be interested in or
what kind of products you're
most likely to want to buy so so i'm
always skeptical
about my own opinions now do i have
opinions like you have
um to some extent and in limited
areas for example in my region where i
live there
is a regeneration of small-scale
agriculture
i have seen over the last 10 or 20 years
blossoming of interest commercial
interest
in organic food uh
and uh you know alternative energy
uh healthier lifestyles are these things
you can see
but how characteristic are they of
what's happening around the planet
uh i don't think very uh the vast
majority of humanity
for very good reasons is simply focused
on getting through the day
and trying to secure enough food and
shelter you know for themselves and
their family
to make any kind of
uh short-term sacrifices you know
you know the the issue that we face is
that um
some problems let you
pay now and get the benefits now
other problems force you to pay now
and then somebody else over elsewhere
later
gets the benefits uh climate change is a
good example of the second one
uh any sacrifice i make for climate
change is
basically not going to accrue to me
personally but to the
general system well most people aren't
in a position
to make those short-term sacrifices for
long-term results
i um i developed a uh computerized
fishing game which was an attempt to
let people role play uh running a
fishing fleet and
make some points about sustainable
harvest and so forth
i played it with a group of maine
fishermen who rather quickly
in the game over harvested the marine
assets and
and collapsed the industry you know and
then we stopped the game and talked
about it and most of them said you know
you're absolutely right this game
exactly captures the features of reality
however i have a big mortgage on my boat
i'm not
able to implement the kinds of
harvesting quotas which would be
required to sustain
the resource long term so you know and
that in a microcosm is
an example of the situation
[Music]
yeah i mean i i completely agree that
that um
it's always good to double check the
echo chambers and the bubbles that we're
in and i'm absolutely
aware that of course i move in in a
bubble
um my sense is that that bubble has been
growing since 1972
since you rang the alarm um
significantly i remember that in 2006 my
phd super second phd supervisor
um professor john todd and uh i was
visiting him in
maine talking to him and his wife nancy
told and you're probably aware of them
they they started the new alchemy
institute in 1969 and
john and nancy are uh good friends of
mine yeah and and i i remember asking in
um john what's changed since you wrote
the briefing paper to
one of the briefing papers to the the
stockholm conference on the environment
um and he he said well back then
there was a handful of us we all knew
each other by name
and we all met each other at every
conference and um
now there are millions and i i sense
that
of course millions is still a drop in
the ocean with
the global population we have but i i
sense that
there are more and more people at
many different parts of society on
everywhere around the world
exploring how to respond to this
situation as more and more people are
waking up to it and
and um of course all those people who
are in
kind of survival mode from one day to
the next
cannot be asked to make sacrifices on
top of
their already subsistence um existence
but
their lives have been conditioned by
the policies and the the systemic design
that
we've created and so basically
people in leadership positions um both
in industry and
in governments um have an opportunity to
engage in a conversation about
redesigning the system and
i like with regard to that like i i
looked at your bio and i saw that your
first degree was in chemistry and i
would
like to ask you a question around if we
look at limits to growth
with regard to the periodic table and a
colleague of mine from the international
futures forum
also a research chemist um
[Music]
worked his way through the entire
periodic table and basically
looked at the projected and realistic
depletion curves of each
one of the elements in it and how
they're used in our
top industries even in all the
sustainable technology that
is now being flogged as the green new
deal and the answer to build that
sustainable utopia that you think is
um absolutely out of the question and
um what what he came to conclude is that
basically we would need to transform our
entire
material culture to be based on
predominantly the four most common
elements carbon oxygen hydrogen and
nitrogen
which we would have to so everything we
use in terms of products would have to
be made mainly out of those elements
in such a way that they could then be
dissolved
and re processed into other products at
the end of their lifetime
and all of that would have to be run by
renewable energy
and he's spent the last 20 years
tracking scientific progress
towards all the research that is
potentially making this a possibility
um because those are the four elements
that nature
builds with and if industry and
political leadership came together to
say okay we need to re-regionalize
production and consumption and we need
to invest
research and development into this tron
carbon oxygen hydrogen nitrogen-based
material culture of the future that is
run on
renewables um
do you think that that could buffer some
of the
um impacts that we're going to see in
the next 10 20
30 years
yes do you think it's possible
like or would you would you would you
agree overall with the argument that
this
friend ian page is his name um has put
forward
well uh before i
comment about his answer to the question
let me comment on his question uh
implicit in what he did was the question
how can humanity sustain its current
trajectory in living standards energy
use
and so forth
i don't think that's a question of
interest to me
our species has been on this planet for
well it depends on how you count but
certainly several hundred thousand years
uh
the lifestyle that your friend is trying
to sustain through his
heroic efforts to develop
carbon oxygen hydrogen and
nitrogen-based technologies
that lifestyle is been here only say
during the last century maybe
two centuries i mean that's uh
that's point one percent of our species
time on this planet
so i don't accord such uh
on a fixed immutable uh
uh nature to the the current mode i mean
there's been lots of different ways to
live on this planet
indeed even today there are thousands of
different kinds of
societies and uh rather than
thinking about how to muster all the
technical resources of humanity to
sustain
a lifestyle uh you know of the rich
white mainly northern
uh peoples industrialized peoples uh
we might look at the globe and
view humanity as one of a large number
of codependent species
and start thinking how can we organize
ourselves you know
in a way that is consistent with the
needs
and the resources that exist
that's the core of my work so just like
i completely agree with you
yeah so now but the narrow answer to
your question uh
is there any chance that we could muster
the technological and economic uh
resources of the planet
to create a society
which uh sustainably uses four
elements no not a not on your life
i mean that's such a remote and i must
say unattractive idea that i
uh i i don't see why somebody would
spend 20 years of their life on it but
you know no that's not my okay i mean i
[Music]
first of all it's in the context of like
i'm i'm not at all
a um sort of technological optimist or
pretending that technology will ride
over the hill to save us
um what i think uh ian was exploring
is how we can
[Music]
make it easier for these future ways of
living that
will be much closer to the past ways of
living that you refer to with
all these other societies that have
lived before
ours um so i think indigenous there are
plenty of examples of
indigenous people um exploiting the
ecosystems but there's also plenty of
examples of indigenous people
working as elegant keystone species
within their local ecosystems and
actually increasing the bioproductivity
and vitality and
health of the system through their their
practices
and um my my sense is that it's not
we're definitely not going to
back to some kind of golden and past but
with the right type of technology we
could possibly
blend a much more regionalized much
simpler
much lower level of consumption but
possibly
higher in meaning and higher in human
relationships and higher in meaningful
relationships to place
and and other life forms future that
um might still have that technological
component and i think that's more
where where the work is coming from
is is that kind of
more regionalized localized lower attack
lower consumption
but blended with some
technology future at all something that
you could
imagine after the work that you've been
doing
yes i could imagine it
but unlikely or i mean
well it's um i'm just
you know i'm thinking back i of course
have been
in discussions about these issues for
almost 50 years now since uh limits to
growth came out
i've been struck by the extent to which
the let us call them social scientists
uh believe that the solution to our
problems lies in technology
and the technologists when they look at
these problems can
conclude that actually the solution lies
off in
social innovation so
my formal training as a scientist in
chemistry
i guess puts me in the second camp
it would be intellectually challenging
to
think how you could uh
build up a society based on four
elements that are
continuously recycled but uh i think
uh you won't succeed and if you did it's
not gonna actually do much for you
anyway i think i have found very useful
to remember
technology is not
an independent value-free
force that comes in looks around
sees a problem and solves it technology
is a value laden
tool wielded developed and wielded
by people who in most cases have their
own
short-term interests you know uh
one of the dominant sources of funding
for new technology in the united states
these days
is the defense department now do you
imagine that the defense department is
trying to create
technologies that will solve the world's
global problems
not my experience drug companies spend a
lot of money on technology
do they spend it on the common uh
problems of poor people
no by and large they spend more money on
things like
restoring hair uh to rich people than
they do
on uh curing uh the diseases
of uh into the third world people
so so when you start talking about
technology it's
uh you need to remember that you're
actually talking
or making assumptions about the goals
and the capacities
of people who feel that they will gain
something by creating a new capability
gaining profit or power
or conceivably the psychological
satisfaction of a job well done but
uh but it's we shouldn't talk about
technology as its own independence thing
absolutely i mean i'm i'm reminded of
buckminster fuller's
statement um when you try to change the
way people think don't tell them what to
think
give them a tool the use of which will
change the way they think
and um pretty much every technology
is such a tool and that starting with
the printing press and even before that
um it has drastically changed the way we
think and how how we see the world
and i mean your work because you
directed the institute
for policy and um social science
and and you also did a lot of work on
games you mentioned one of them
and i mean these these artworks are
actually one of my favorites
is this book that you co-authored with
linda booth swinney the
the systems thinking playbook um because
again i think that these
these games are technologies that change
the way people think that book is a
technology that changed
the way people think so how on two
levels in terms of creating
systemic ecological literacy for people
in place at the local level
um through games like this um and
also to creating the same kind of
awareness with policy makers
what with you what from my perspective
right now seems like a rather bleak
um assessment of where we're heading and
what would you suggest policymakers
could do
um to
prepare for the future that you're
seeing and what would you suggest
local communities could do in this
context okay
so um once again i'll just point out
that you use the term bleak
[Music]
and of course from the perspectives of
of our perspectives i mean you and i are
among those who benefit very much
uh from the current situation so when
someone threatens the current situation
it seems
bleak to us uh the future may be
uh just the opposite of bleak for the
majority of people living on the planet
uh but what to do
a central problem of our
society rich and poor
is that we have developed
a set of institutions
expectations and
and other social uh mechanisms
fundamentally based on and dependent on
the assumption
of continued growth
i i was asked recently uh by
the site which as i'm sure you know is a
common german
news weekly to talk about whether or not
humanity could get along without growth
uh and my answer in part was yes
absolutely no problem actually
for the vast majority of its entire
existence on this planet it has
gotten along without growth that's not
the problem the problem is going from
rapid forward movement to being uh
quiescent you know it's like riding a
bicycle it's relatively easy to ride a
bicycle
and it's also relatively easy to stand
next to your bicycle holding it there
still but to get from rapid forward
movement
to be dismounting and getting up that is
a
skill set which if you don't master it
can cause a lot of damage
and that's what we face in our society
we
don't know uh certainly at the community
or at the national level
how to envision a future that's
attractive and which doesn't
have growth in it growth
plays an extremely important role
politically and socially politically
growth is lets politicians uh
reach compromises which don't give
everybody what they want
because they can promise that they'll
get more later
you know and as soon as you
eliminate the promise of growth and it
starts to look like a zero-sum game at
which point
uh democracies don't function very well
actually i think it's one of the key
problems facing western democracies at
the moment real growth is by and large
uh gone away and we're now in a position
of
uh zero sum negotiations and
uh it doesn't work very well uh under
those circumstances
so what can you do well uh
let's start with population
it seems as though fertility is
declining
certainly it is declining objectively in
some nations
china and japan
are uh russia and others
so that that's an objective fact rather
than fight it
by offering subsidies or you know
banning uh birth control it would be
useful for
uh governments to start trying to
understand how they can run a system
in which the population isn't
continuously expanding
in which you don't need more and more
building stock in which tax revenues
don't keep going up and up and up
and which there's not a steady flow of
young people to support the old people
in their
pensions and so forth a lot of
interesting problems which could be
addressed
and uh would be it'll actually be very
challenging
until we have answers to those questions
we're going to ignore
the fact that we are overpopulated
so one thing i would start with at the
community level at the
individual level at the national level
uh
start playing this thought experiment
that growth is going to stop
and that you need to fashion the society
which can function
uh within the constraints of serial
growth there are solutions
it's just that we haven't bothered to
look for them
that'd be one thing at the local level
this can be things like
deciding what is an attractive
population for your community
and understanding you know how you'll
get there and then
uh stay there uh at the
national level it gets off into issues
of tax revenue and so forth
that's one thing to do uh another thing
to do
is uh
to start imagining other indicators of
success
i've been struck uh by the extent
to which the swedish approach
to the virus has been forced
into the metric two metrics really
number of deaths
short term and uh gmp growth
and people uh use those two numbers in
comparison with
those two numbers from other countries
to decide whether or not they think the
swedish
uh experiment was successful well
leaving aside the fact that we're still
in the early stages is it's epidemic so
it's
it's kind of like trying to call a race
a marathon on the basis of who's ahead
after three minutes
uh it's clearly in sweden
there are many other factors going on uh
to define the psychological social
economic well-being
of the people and uh we don't pay
attention to them because we bylaws
don't have indicators of them
so it would be useful for communities to
start trying to think through how they
can define
and gather record and report
a somewhat more diverse set of
indicators of success
if everything is either black or white
it's hard uh to make a choice but if
you start to see very large uh varieties
of gray then you know
there are other options available too so
you know i could go on but those two
things one
starting systematically to explore the
mechanisms the social
the economic mechanisms for dealing with
a stable population
or even declining population and then
secondly
coming up with other kinds of indicators
you know the japanese have a saying if
your only
tool is a hammer everything looks like a
nail well if your only tool is the gnp
everything looks like a economic problem
yeah and this is fascinating that even
four years before
your book came out um in 1972
robert kennedy gave a speech in which he
very clearly
spoke to the deficiency of um gdp
as as a sensible indicator and and we're
still
using it and but but so many of your
colleagues from the
bulletin group and all the other um
international forums
of uh 4i of um sustainability experts
are now working on things like the we
well-being along the we all alliance
trying to create these new indicators
trying to create more qualitative
indicators
of growth and and i'm sure you you know
the work that hazel henderson and
freddie of couple did a while ago
on this this shifting medically from
quantitative to qualitative growth like
making a distinction that
in in nature lots of things grow
normally they grow in a logistics curve
a
logistic curve rather than an
exponential curve meaning that at some
point
they they begin to not grow and continue
to grow in numbers but in
quality in relationships and experience
um and
in that sense
of course it always depends on what kind
of growth we're talking about
i understand limits to growth was very
clearly
not about the gdp growth but about the
resource and energy youth
growth and continuing um
what do you think about these
initiatives like
the we all alliance well-being alliance
all these
there's a huge group of people now
working on how could we redesign
capitalism or even replace it with
a more functional economic system that
doesn't
uh structurally drive the behavior that
incentivizes the exploitation of people
and planet and
also just wanted to add that i
absolutely
agree with your assessment that we are
the privileged ones from this situation
and i'm completely aware that um that
i'm um
part of that ten percent that is
over consuming to a very large extent
and having
a disproportionate impact on the planet
compared to um
i think it's about sixty percent of the
world's population
actually have to share three percent of
the economic wealth
while ten percent of the population
um have eighty percent of the economic
wealth
um so inequality um is a big issue
here too well i'm happy that a growing
number of people are looking at
to find alternative indicators uh you
held up
that book uh system thinking playbook
one of the exercises in there
is uh you know called frame that's as uh
called um secret code
and it um it shows how
you look for solutions within the box
and often the solutions we need aren't
inside that box you have to
think outside the box and uh the system
of ac
indicators that we have now constitute a
box they uh
they define the problem and they are
currently used to
evaluate possible responses in fact
the really good responses uh don't show
up very well with those indicators you
need new indicators to
to take you in in the right direction um
coming back to this issue of growth yes
our book uh
could have been called the limits to
physical growth
we weren't talking about uh
non-quantitative uh growth we were
talking about
food materials soil so forth
uh and the point we made in there i
think bears uh
repeating physical growth is not going
to continue forever on a finite planet
it will stop i'm
you know so that's not the the debate
here
the question is that's of interest to us
what will be the mechanisms that stop
it will they be limitations that we
proactively define
and impose on ourself or will they
be limitations imposed on us by the
environment
to make this concrete let's take
population
you know population grows when the birth
rate is higher than the death rate
if you want population to quit growing
you can either
reduce the birth rate or increase the
death rate
generally speaking proactively the
measures that reduce the birth rate are
ones we find more
attractive more consistent with
individual
liberty and choice uh
and those are uh range from female
education
to uh family planning campaigns
uh et cetera on the other side the
factors that increase the death rate are
the same as they've always been
famine pestilence and war
and generally speaking when we look at
those options we don't think them
to be very attractive uh so those are
the choice we face but not only with
population with
energy use with food consumption uh
and so forth and
you know what you're asking really is
will this growing
group of people interested in
alternatives
rise up in numbers of power quickly
enough
to begin enforcing proactive limitations
on the growth
or will they be too late
in which case we will just sit here and
wait for
uh nature uh to decide how it's going to
limit our earth i mean there is an
equality issue that is really central
and i
i personally of course i would agree
that
um coming on to eight billion people
is too many humans for the capacity
carrying capacity of the planet and
we've pretty much as humanity been in
overshoot
since since i was born i was born in
1971 and we went into overshoot just
before that
um but
sometimes this conversation about
there's just too many of us
obscures the fact that it's really a
as you alluded to like the winners of
these crisis
um are the over consuming
10 that have
the the large part of um the impact
and um so so really the the uh
way of equitably or re-addressing the
inequity issue
would be to um respond to this not
like the population growth as you also
alluded to
is naturally beginning to seem to be
seems to be slowing down if we
engage in the measures you mentioned
like educating women and so on we can
probably do it
even faster but really it is about
changing the patterns of consumption and
a while ago i think when the 45th
anniversary of limits to growth happens
you were interviewed by somebody in
german tv and they put out a little
video that i watched yesterday and in it
you also made the point that
there's no no way that we can um avoid
the i thought you mentioned the word
collapse but you must use the different
words
breakdown or this is not continuing
um and you then said the only way we
have is
a change of cultural and societal norms
um but that seemed to me
still leaving the door open that we
could
engender such a change of cultural and
societal norms
um are you are you hopeful that that's
possible
it is possible is it likely
yeah that's a different one um
you know i um
so i think about these things a lot and
uh you know i spent 50 years
trying to help people understand uh
their realistic options and and start uh
choosing a bit more wisely for the long
term
i would say by and large i failed i i
don't
think the planet is going to evolve on
of course
any different from i having been around
than it would have if
i hadn't been conceived um
anything is possible and of course many
things will happen i mean
the one of my sorrows is that i won't be
alive 100 years from now to see what
things look like
they will be very different than they
are now
i uh you know i remember i
uh i gave uh i
i've given many speeches in vienna to uh
different
groups and one of the things i've uh
often said to them starting already uh
10 15 years ago was that
the next 20 years we'll see more changes
in their life than the last hundred
and in the case of austria that's a huge
difference because 100 years ago they
were a monarchy and a large empire
uh but i think uh it's true i mean if
you
you just uh look at what's happened even
over the last uh
six months the the pace of change is
astonishing
so uh so when you ask me is it possible
yes anything is possible
uh will it be likely and will it be
effective you know those
that that remains to be seen i've uh
i've been impressed by the extent that
um things
usually take longer than you expect them
to at least the positive ones
yeah and so
um i don't ex i don't expect personally
to be alive when that has happened
did i ask you a question like there's
there's a
there's something like i've learned a
lot from the writings of your late
ex-wife donella
and um i always found it fascinating
that there's a there's an article that
gets quoted a lot that she wrote called
um leverage points
to change a system to intervene in a
system
and what i find particularly interesting
about this article is that i've
discovered that
there are two versions of the same
article one that that you wrote
significantly earlier where the leverage
points stop at the higher highest
leverage point being called
at the level of the paradigm and it's
basically still within that framing of
the kind of
kunyan paradigm shift from from this to
that
and and then um towards the end of her
life
there's this other version that came out
that
where the highest point is going beyond
paradigms
and then that was elaborated on
in in a way in something that was
published posthumously first in a
journal i think it was whole earth or
some
something um a little piece called
dancing with systems that then also
ended up in her
um systems thinking book that that was
published
and when i sense there and that's i'm
wanting to check this with you is is a
shift in
in perspective which is saying okay all
we've been talking about
is the rational scientific data driven
frame of where we're likely to
to head and the rational scientific data
driven
um perspective on how likely is
a societal change like this but there
are so many other ways of
knowing and we we mentioned that so many
other societies have very different
world views and have lived and are
living um
on on our planet at the same time that
they are
holding other um
transformation possible i'm not saying
any kind of
things i'm just saying in letting in
more diverse ways of knowing and coming
home
into um understanding that so much of
our world view is driving this
unsustainable behavior
um is do you think that there's any
any hope in that and also do you did you
experience this shift beyond
just the scientific paradigm into this
going beyond paradigms
notion in in your late ex-wife
so the evolution of uh
danella's writing i think reflects two
things first
she became wiser and uh more spiritual
actually as she uh got older
and also she came to understand how hard
it is for people
to understand the term paradigm so
some of the elaboration up above
paradigm was simply her way of
cutting the pie in a way that might make
it easier
for people to understand
um
eight i'm going to speak loosely now a
kind of
common of humanity
is to be happy
[Music]
there are two ways to be happy uh
unhappiness is when you don't get what
you want
so you can become happy either by
getting what you want
or wanting what you get
and we are in a period now where we're
not going to get
what we want this notion
uh promulgated by the economist you know
of of
uh ever expanding higher and higher
uh quality of life and uh and more etc
uh that's just a fantasy we're moving in
a different direction i don't know yet
how that will unfold but i do know that
as time goes by we will
alter our desires and expectations to be
more in conformity with what we actually
have you see that actually happening now
with the virus
people are adjusting
their thoughts about what constitutes a
normal lifestyle because they just
couldn't stand to continue being unhappy
about
having to give up things which in the
old days they thought were essential
so part of this way of adjusting will be
in
knowing and you know
i keep coming back to this our species
has been on this planet for several
hundred thousand years
i remember when i was little and so
enthralled with
uh modern science and modern knowledge i
i more or less implicitly thought that
for the first couple hundred thousand
years people's head must have been empty
because it didn't have
all this wonderful knowledge in it you
know
but of course that's not true uh in some
ways
uh those earlier examples of us
were more sophisticated more nuanced and
more complex
than we are today they had to be because
if they didn't uh
have a very very subtle understanding of
their environment they
would die off uh
much less a threat uh today so they had
different ways of knowing
uh those ways will come back they still
exist
in places and in aspects and they will
be re-accentuated
and so you you think that this this uh
adding going beyond paradigms wasn't
because i always
took it as speaking to the the value of
holding even if they're not fully
commensurate multiple
ways of perceiving reality and multiple
world views
uh in parallel in order to um
draw some insight from all of them and
because any perspective will always have
a blind spot
to to basically make wiser decisions
because we're not just drawing from one
particular rigid way of knowing with its
own um epistemological blinkers and
yeah that was my interpretation of
of that edition so i i agree with you
you might note incidentally anybody
who's
watching this if you go on the web and
type in
danella meadows intervening in a system
you'll pull up
uh the article which i think is a very
profound
statement uh about the problems that we
face uh paradigms uh ways of structuring
knowledge are by their nature
incomplete and wrong and so
you can't avoid that but at least you
can be open
to your choice of paradigms and you can
deliberately
choose to look at an issue through a
variety of different paradigms
each of which may give you some useful
information
it's the people who are stuck in one
paradigm who think that
that particular way of knowing is
somehow
immutable eternal and uh and
divinely granted uh to us without error
they're in trouble because uh inevitably
they
are going to misunderstand the situation
and make wrong choices
so to to wind up um
you you said earlier that um
one thing you regret is that you won't
be around in a hundred years
to see what will have happened
um i know this is a bit of a tricky
question and you're also fine to say
that
you don't want to make a conjecture
there but um
if things go more the positive way how
how would you
how could you imagine um life
to be like in 100 years for our
future ancestors
well i i speculate about that i don't
imagine that i have any great insights
about it
it's certainly not a matter of
scientific
discovery that leads me to these
thoughts but 100 years from now
the planet will have a climate
very different from the one it has now
similar to what it has had
at times in the past and since
our civilization our modes of
agricultural production
our ways of generating and using energy
are so uh in
intertwined with the climate
the fact that the climate is changing
means that
those modes will change our civilization
will be very different
a hundred years from now than it is now
population will be lower
and my guess is that the modes of social
organization
will be much more local
and i'll use the term uh despite its
negative kind tribal you know it's uh
it's interesting
uh in the early days when i was
advocating
uh for change people uh
change because uh the current policies
are leading us
uh in the wrong direction people would
say well
i i guess that means you're in favor of
communism or you're in favor of a
dictatorship
if you don't like democracy and my
response was you know
in the 200 000 years that we have been
on this planet we've had many many
different ways
of organizing ourselves dictatorship
and uh fascism and so forth these are
some ways that we've done we've done
many other ways the way which has
actually been most stable
and existed over the longest period time
is tribal
uh you know a mechanism by which
relatively small groups typically
uh genetically interconnected
collaborate and make decisions
um so i i think that will come back you
know
it's interesting to look at what
happened in europe after the collapse of
the roman empire
there was four five hundred years where
uh
we went back to being uh mainly
a city-state mechanism for
organization before feudalism and
monarchies and so forth
emerged
it it requires a mode of organization
where people feel some identity
with others the only
thing uh your own perceived interest
is if somehow a collective
group that you identify with will be
better off and
uh you know one of one of the issues uh
we confront
today is uh
that migration travel
movements have broken down this sense
of identification with others
so i think probably that will re-emerge
uh settlement patterns will be very
different uh
parts of the planet are now in the
process of becoming uninhabitable
it was 125 degrees in baghdad two days
ago
i can't imagine what it's like and of
course
soon it will be 130 degrees in baghdad
and at roughly 135 degrees uh
life is becomes impossible so uh parts
of the planet because of temperature
sea level rise uh declining moisture
will become uninhabited
my panels will differ uh
i think we will move much closer back to
a period where people are more
responsible for producing the energy
that they need uh in traditional
societies roughly 80 percent of the
population produce
energy and 20 are administrators
military
religious leaders who use the energy
uh in our society it's three or four
percent of the people who are producing
primary
uh agricultural energy but as oil and
gas
uh declined uh we're going to have to go
back
and work to using a variety of sunlight
as
for energy sources so it's just going to
put more of us back in the role of
producing you know these are sort of
general speculations they don't get to
the
some of the most important things are we
happy are we
healthy are we peaceful we could be all
of those things or we could be
none of that that those are choices
which won't be imposed on us those are
choices that we still have
to make ourselves that's a very
important point
i also appreciate that the i mean and i
would agree with you
that you what you didn't um paint into
this picture of the future is this
ludicrous pathway that some of
the multi-billionaires of the planet are
um sketching out of of going off planet
of asteroid mining of
um missions to mars and and some
some kind of technological savior future
because
the energetic and material basis for
that kind of solution will
simply not be there oh that's just such
a silly idea
you know i um
a friend of mine was involved in this
experiment out in arizona called the
biosphere
where all three people who lived in it
yeah yeah so for
a huge amount of money and a huge amount
of technological expertise were expended
to create an enclosed
system where i don't know just a dozen
people
could try to live sustainably for a year
and it failed
because you know yeah it failed uh
we we haven't we weren't able with all
that money and all that expertise
uh to create uh a sustainable biosphere
with uh we haven't been able to create a
sustainable earth
the notion that we're now somehow going
to go off
uh i don't know to mars or the moon or a
space station
and suddenly uh solve all these problems
that's just
um it's beyond silly it's um
you know it's the last desperate gasp
uh of people who don't want to
acknowledge that they themselves are
actually the cause of the problem
wonderfully put i completely and utterly
agree on that and
in terms of biosphere 2 i always found
it fascinating that like i know
three people who spent two years in in
biosphere two
and and one of them was a marine
biologist who was in charge of
maintaining
the reef ecosystem and the earliest
warning sign that they had
that the entire system was beginning to
go into
failure were basically two one of them
was the response of the reef and the
other one
was the atmospheric composition in in
their little bubble
um but the the way that reef ecosystems
and marine ecosystems because they tend
to be the buffer of
any kind of atmospheric problem or this
non-functional disequilibrium um
is is a lesson to us that now that we
see coral
bleaching and and reef die off all over
the planet we should really take that
lesson at least from
which is probably one of the few like
they really biosphere 2 gave us
a clear example of our hubris of
thinking that we can actually
design complex dynamic systems of that
nature do
the kind of things that life has evolved
over 3.8 billion years
um just by assembly like a machine
um and
yeah for me that that
lesson is is one that we still haven't
fully learned yet people still believe
that um we have all these amazing high
technologies but
really compared to what the technology
of life
achieves it their their
kitty hawk and the wright brothers uh
a friend of mine um amy lovens has
coined a phrase which i find is very
relevant here
um some
systems that we build must be
fail safe you know when you build a
nuclear reactor
the consequences of failure are so
horrendous that you have to say to
yourself it is
fail-safe it cannot fail certainly
a space station which is going to house
these people has to be fail-safe because
if it
makes a mistake you you don't have a
fallback
and amrey has pointed out uh as
and there's of course uh enormous
empirical evidence for this
you can't build plc systems so
it is simply outside the capacity of
humanity to design
a complex system that is feel safe and
so rather than try to do that
you need design systems which fail
safely where you can have mistakes
and although they are cause problems
they don't cause catastrophe
and they become the basis for learning
how to do it better
you asked what can we do well another
thing we can
do is to begin looking around at the
systems we depend on
and ask how we can
design them in a way that lets them fail
safely
because they are going to fail
i mean earlier you said that um
we either can get happy by um
well basically how do you say it again
um
liking what we get or um if you don't
get what you want what will you get
yeah what you get um for me that
deep her insight and also hearing you
really it inspired me for for many many
years and you
many other people around the world same
as you did
earlier but you you don't think that
your 50 years of ringing your alarm bell
and 30 years of trying to
get people to take different
paths will have had a long-term effect
um it's
somewhat making me reflect on
how do i spend my time um do you feel
like having spent your time this way
um do you do you regret some of it what
would you have done
differently um i'm i'm personally
getting to a point
in this sense of love what you get um
of really coming down to appreciating
the beauty that is still in front of us
and
really loving life again and loving um
[Music]
the miracle of human relationships and
of being in relationship
with with an ecosystem with a place with
whatever
tickles your fancy some people like
forests other people like the ocean or
the mountains
um what would you
live differently now that you look back
at 50 years of
um what you yourself said might not have
made the difference that at some point
i'm sure you were hoping it would make
well if you've lived 50 years and think
that you've done everything perfectly
right i think you're
fooling yourself certainly
i if i knew 50 years ago
what i know now i
would have made some different choices i
don't
regret uh i have no major regrets
uh regret actually isn't a very useful
emotion anyway uh
and plus i don't have now the option of
going back 50 years
and doing it in a different way
um
i have evolved an ethic
which guides my own behavior and which
uh i don't regret i
it's it's it hasn't uh i don't think
it's made the world
a drastically different place but it's
uh it's been a
a decent uh
beacon uh from modern life that is
i've endeavored uh in all everything i
do
all my work my personal relations
uh to leave people better off
than i found them it doesn't mean i'm
obligated to solve all their problems
which of course i couldn't do
anyway but at least i don't lie to them
and i don't rip them off
if everybody did that uh
a lot of these problems would go away
yeah i mean that's again buckminster
fuller comes to mind he said
in the end only integrity is going to
count
and and i feel like that's what you're
speaking to as has been your
motto for living the life the way you've
lived it
thank you so much for this conversation
and and also thank you for pushing back
on my
um not so youthful anymore enthusiasm
and
and and maybe fantastical views of
what might still be possible i often
when i give talks
end with with a quote um that
we're now at a point where we have to do
the impossible because
the probable has become unthinkable and
to some extent unconscionable
and and that's why i'm allowing myself
to still
speak about fantastical solutions
and holding both possibilities lightly
in terms of what
what future we're stirring into also
having a three-year-old daughter
has given me a kind of obligation to
still see a path into the future that
that could be hopeful
for all daughters and all sons
but but i appreciate
that kind of pushing back on some of
of that from you because i i deeply
value your insights so thank you very
much
so it's been a pleasure talking with you
thank you very much thank you so much
i'll just stop the report